We get-together
morning before I start I want to apologize to that front kind
of corner if I disappear behind the polar it's not my fault so.
If you want to see most of the time and move to the side-of-the-road where...hiding behind the big concrete
...but other than that ...morning a hyper all
...is fresh this morning as I am I was not up like last night looking at all
the san-francisco balls and trying at the...was my hotel room being good
and diligent...I'm fresh for this morning who else is...excellent
whether that all right so we're going to talk about as your's no...
databases a service called as a document db my name's ryan I'm one of the program
...on the team in case you haven't seen me or heard me before he
so my embarrassing je don's on video that's gone viral
...spread everywhere good not many people I have some dignity
left that's also ok so it's...take a look please remember
...decision will be a slider the your code feasible evil?
And, that's all right so what
...going to drive I have a couple of ideas I thought depending on how many people epub calling
...we could have some coffee...people seem to be fresh so what we're
...do today is going to have a look at document devices just quickly briefly as a show of
hands who's never use the document database before a lot of people all right all
right so you do a quick recap of document devices what they're good for what
are not-so-good for kind of vague difference between them and relational
databases who has used some other document database so like among
...or raven couch tv
...the big favorites that you want a
...db user...dvds?
We'll.
Just to give an idea of what you guys have been doing we're going to do a
quick intro recap to document db it's not going to be a the?
We're not just been too much time on that we want to try get down to the building
apps...the tips and tricks for building apps because that's where you want to spend a lot of time and
we'll take a quick look ...ahead we've got some feedback from people that say
we really want to know what you guys doing what's on your
road ahead and we're not really usually very good sharing that kind of info
publicly because it commits us to stuff but, that's okay I'll say what's, what's,
what's on...so, what is a document database document...is?
The type device that is very good at dealing with
dyson data...documents that look like that
...read...you don't really need to as long as you get the idea that it's I
...hierarchical kind of...documents it's got some nesting in
...it can horizon a that can have...documents and the idea is that...
thing isself-contained entity that describes some.
Some entity that you're working with...b customer with autos and
...lines and products or a contact with addresses
an contact details or anything that's kind
of like self-contained into a document and that's I think
...the name comes from and if I had a time machine I'd go back in time and try
and influence whoever called a document...document advice I try and get them
...something else because it kinda creates a little bit of confusion but,
when you think about these document devices there really are
the self-contained documents...
when you deal with a relational database like sequel server?
...dealing with tables you dealing with records...records
...to other records and to get the entity what you actually go to the
dues you gotta go and join a bunch of a whole bunch of tables together and compose the
entity on-the-fly document databases take a different approach they say hey instead of
me doing those computation calculation
...on-the-fly what you should do is model your documents as these kind of
...complete entities and there's a very good reason why.
There are some papers and studies that say document devices scale
at the internet scale they perform a whole lot better than relational databases
...this is one of the very big reasons relational databases have to do a
lot of work on-the-fly when you start joining ffifteen tables together to compose
...and every time you...and entity it has to go and kind
of break that up and righted to fifteen different tables and maintain locks and all that kind of stuff...was doing
that or the document database you working on that single document entity so we don't need to
...and...anything else all we do is we persist just that one into...the whole
...all right so there's a fundamental difference between those two so when you start working
with document devices think about that.
So, there really are good to those kind of document they're not so well...to that kind of
...now that's also adjacent document and, I could put that into a document
advice no problem at all okay ...work.
And, I could go
...search or query full things by id all by text
okay this kind of document...
is probably better served out of something like edges search or elastic social
...laurel one of the search engines why because most of the searching that you can do on
...document is worth...blocker text...you're going to be wanting to do full-text
that makes a or full-text searching fuzzy logic searching...matching sound
...matching all of that kind of stuff and that's probably better...suited to a search engine rather
...database changes something like
...probably better...in?
As research than in document in a document advice will work
show you can do it but...going to stop you but there are other options.
And, lastly.
They're definitely not for those kind of data
document okay and I've got a lot of people come to me and...this is also how do I stole my
...documents in as a document database.
Document...are not for those kind of document write...really
...for jason documents not where documents all...now if you want to
...or content management solution that took...documents and you want to
...in something like as a document db you probably code right because what you do is you would create a
meta that metadata documents and, in that jason you would put all the searchable curable fields that you want
to query on you put that in the jason and then using document
...attachment property you would attach the word document the binary to the metadata...
and process that in document db because what we then do is we take a binary we put it
into blob storage and, now we are knee-deep and index the
small metadata file so what I'm trying index these things if you want to indexing and searching inside of your
...documents office documents sharepoint so much better option
for you it's designed to do that sort of thing?
Seems my clicker has a very limited range.
All right so one of the things that have
...document devices by far the most popular
database at the moment if you look at stats on the
...growing devices there is one whose name shall not be...the room?
That is probably the third or fourth most popular database in terms of growing
...couple years...a very good reason why developers...flocking to
document devices and that's because they love document devices and document
devices love developers mostly document advice if you
...yesterday on the data who was in
the session yesterday on the foundations nobody so you...have seen
me there yesterday how developer friendly
document databases onstage on-the-fly...to make a change to an application
and without going through a whole modeling exercise and that without going through a whole or
...mapping exercise all I did was open
...visual studio make a change to a model class they...change the ui and I could
been persist a new field in the database right and that's how easy it is
you can and it's so good for those the way we build applications that.
Remembers and just doing a quick scan of the audience but he remembers when we bolts
systems.
Where we would...take a six-month planning phase and we would sit
down and we would do this whole complicated data modeling exercise and,
then often that six-month kind of
...we then going to planning and we'd figure out how to map that into a domain
object and eventually about a year later we would actually start building an application right we don't
build applications like that anymore we sit down we go right I got a great idea we open up
and ide whatever that is we...coding and now we just want to source that and retrieved from
...is that's how we work and we want to make a change we go back into the application we make
...code change we don't have to go through that whole process of kind of, you know, taking
...offline updating all apply update scripts the change the schemer eccentric such a
related to create these crazy schemas to deal with the
fact that not all records have those property ... that you just go in and,
you work with them what we really like about document databases as well as...notion of
low impedance who love sitting down and mapping your?
Programming language...dot net type into a database type.
...that love saying that this domain object
...is actually this field in that database table...most of my in
properties that fielding map table and change its type and do this horrible mapping thing
...doing that many people all these things you don't actually have to do that most of
the time your views
in your view models if you working in ajax and knock up or what you know,
all of those kinds of tools...probably already working with a
...follow some form right you working javascript working with
...follow ready...you've got this...object that will be cool if I could just take the
...object...persistence and get the...object back and, bonded to...and
that's exactly what document devices allow you to do...so it just works?
That's hard.
By the time it should just work right and it's fast it's...to get going it's...to use them
...to develop against them and for most part they perform really,
really well if you've done the some due diligence
...just because they're kind of really quick and really easy to get up and running a lot
of people get sorrowful subtle for a particular way and without doing any
...how they should model...all how they should designer entities
...they get stuck by...stuck and I find that
the six months in the data model isn't working for them anymore okay because they're apps...too big
...the documents of going-to...queries...slowing down or whatever the case maybe you'll still have all
kinds of issues but it really is much quicker to go in refactoring data model a
and kinda keep going.
So, as a document db fully managed highly scalable...document
...as a service right yes it is only available in as
...today and, that's.
Where we are?
When we started out with us it's been a long road for us we've been working
on this probably two years around about two
years when we first started out we slowed up when?
Various people with film or various groups...microsoft came to the
...the data group right because we part of the sign group that
build sequel server believable we're also part of the same group that bowls...research and,
all the other cool data like all those kind of other cooled...data services
were part of the same group and I came to that group and I said I guys we really want to use
a document database which is the document database you recommend for us and we kind of
...looking around and the this one
...some cases that one-word some cases but largely we when happy as a as a
data group with any of the databases that were out there so we actually wanted to
take a step back and say can we do some things better...and these of become
...for our full kind of polls that we want to believe
...all right the fact that we really want to be...enabled query of the schema free that
...a bit ofa buzzword right because
you're document actually has some kind of a schema because as soon as you structure document in a particular
...infers...right so...schema
...were schema flexible because we allow you to change that structure really easily but
that has some kind of a...right but what we really want to be able to do is not just allow you to
...these documents in whatever format or whatever schema
...like...we want to very quickly and very easily to be able to query them and,
that's where we found a lot of these databases breakdown a lot of them allow you to quickly and easily
stall...jason documents but in order to be able to go and efficiently query them you have to
...define indexes.
Now soon as you define an index you've...the schema right because the
...document changes if it doesn't match what...schema says you're not
...query for it as soon as you start working.
And, you start...evolving your data models, you know,
I have to go and kind of rebuild indexes you have to wait for them to rebuild and all that constant we
wanted to be able to take adjacent document with any arbitrary kind
of properties any level of nesting any arbitrary property in the document persisted in the database
and needed to be able to query using index on any property in...document and none of that when we
...none of the databases on the market and I don't believe any on the
...dice lol offer that right.
So, that was one of the very first thing is that we that we that we set out to
...and we set...
We've been to microsoft research guys and we said to them
...us because we don't know-how to do
this must be possible anything's possible given enough time and money we don't know-how to do this
can you help and the microsoft research guys revising they were
to our engineers and...bolts...you type of index so a lot of
...if you've done any database workload databases share some common index
engines
...we don't we have a new index engine that runs as a document
...now a lot of people have been asking about details of that index engine.
we have a...paper that will be published shortly and, dahmer...principle engineer
pe will be presenting at a number of database conferences shortly on our in
...and how it works but, that was one of one of the fundamental differences that we...that
we worked on the other one that we wanted to nile was concept of multi
...transactions right everybody loves in sequel server
on any relational system that I can start...transaction I can
...number...the different entities different tables different
rows and I can commit the transaction and if anything goes wrong halfway between
...transaction roll-out and the databases back into a
consistent site now as soon as you move over into the...sequel world
into the other document devices many of them don't allow that behavior
...now do but, many don't...do that so you give up
those notion of consistent...atomic transactions as soon as you move to one of these
devices and that causes problems right we've seen some horrendous looking code that developers of
had to write in their applications to deal with the fact that
...unique compensation undo rollback and all sorts of crazy
things so we really wanted to mail the fact that we want you to be able to
do multi...transactions so?
Do one operation that touches a number of different documents and if that operation
succeeds commit all those documents if the operation files rollback out and leave
the databases ones and then we really wanted to kind of the
...to come into...together?
We really want to make this thing
...and we really want to make this thing perform and we really want to kind of offered
...price points that are small increments that you can
adjust up...down...by the...
you know, all of those kinds of things that we found that taking a product was
designed to run on a server and hosting at server for use a service didn't really give you that
those capabilities so this is what we set out to do and this is how we believe as
a document db differentiates itself from the other databases that are up.
If we take a look.
Document db very well-suited to webm...mobile applications
...that's the only kind of application you can...document db with
...it'll work brilliantly and a line-of-business...it'll work brilliantly
in a normal enterprise kind of application it'll work fantastically well
in an imc application in fact many of
our very large customers are running imc applications to
...on document db we have a vehicle manufacturer that every time you start and stop...those
...telemetry message that gets persisting document db it's actually kind of scary what vehicle
manufacturers collect about...just by the way.
I'm not saying which vehicle manufacturer...one I drive so, what are the other things that we want try to do is
this reliable and predictable performance okay when?
When we started out one of
the very first thing that we said is that we don't want to have this notion of
a noisy neighbor problem because that's the problem that puts a lot of people from a
...a service is that your application
is usually impacted by what...neighbor on your boxes doing?
And, for us that was an absolute nonnegotiable so,
we...make sure that when you create your database when you put
...documents into your collection of for documents we...make sure that
was completely isolated from anything else happening on the machine so fast predictable
...consistency that's what we radio gainful and...really all gainful celeste
We think we've done well with elastic scale we've
heard from feedback during preview in the early color weeks of gi that we can
this...that we can do better and we will but also some other kind of things that were.
Shooting...
And, then really with...document db at
its this document itemized thing it really is about rapid development right.
We took a couple of bets when we started out we said well how do we
get developers to start using document db as quickly as possible and
eases why was give them tools that are familiar with.
...I'm going to new query language that you have to...learn how to how to do
...divested you...inventor new protocol...inventing you kind of
...to...documents okay there's a way that everybody loves it already
school jason use dyson right there's a lot of work that's gone into
...developers love javascript so let's try and use javascript where we can
...and really integrate javascript into the database engine so we hoping that it's easy to
...get up and running.
And, then the fact that it's fully...is also okay I just create
the database within a couple of minutes if I arkansas...against.
One of the things as well as that we also want to make sure that it's not just the service that kind of is there on its
own all right we are part of the as your ecosystem
one of my show that when you bowled a web app or logic app and api app
or mobile app that you can use document db one of my show that
when you deal machine learning kind of stuff on the cool machine learning things that you saw in the
keynote one of my shoulder document db can be part of that.
Rbi so when you want to run your reports and you want to do analytics and offs questions of your data we
want-to make sure a document devious part of that so today we
...support search so when you have a search account you can go in and creates a document
...they call it a data source code direct connection but you can point edit either
sql or document db and then I will go and index and
crawl through...db and...all right so
...more complicated writing code or double write code put in document
...in search and trying to keep
...now you just put in document db point search at the middle figure it out for you dupe we've got a
...connector so-if you want-to do these complicated running along writing map
reduce jobs to do aggregates and averages and counts and
...and all those sorts of things you can fire off using our
didn't connector you can run those jobs and then...data back into document db if you want
or anyone else what are the cool things...connector is.
We have some customers that are into the approaching triple digit terabyte
...of data in document db they storing lots and lots and lots and lots and lots of
data and I when I when I...using the ado...I found that the jobs would run
for a really long-time and that's because we were going through eighty...data now
dupes really good at doing that map reduce thing but we thought well is there a wide to...that even quicker so
...connect you can actually give a document db query the...equipment...
will only fetch that data that...you're interested in and then kind of work through
that rather than fetching everything it'll any fetch what you...fetch.
And, then work has begun integrating into all these other kind of tools and
technologies and, they should ...
...so little that what...you db cost so,
from as little as I think it's.
I don't have an undue look for one-hour for
document db database is three cents.
For a...I think it's less than a cup of coffee or much less than a cup of
coffee okay so you can get going really, really quick really,
really easy there are a couple of things
...that are must mention all right and you'll see as we go on through the rest
of the session I hope you'll get an understanding of kind of how things work these are
price at a collection...so...uses raven...
Pay attention visa charged
a collection level and that's because a collection in document db is a very different concept
in a very different notion to a collection among...rival.
Hindsight says we should have probably given a different time we shouldn't of
...collection use people expect to use it like very using mongolian
...collections among the guys and they documentations
says think of a collection like a table and think of a document like a
We don't want people to think of collections like that.
We want people to think of collections as I partition of data you can
stick any data into a collection not just tighter of the same type.
And, there's
a number reasons for that because of features like being able to do multi
...transactions
...within collections eventually we'll have some future features that are also going to kind of
make more sense of why we see collections as...
of heterogeneous documents rather than the documents of the same type.
So, when you start our planning for your application?
Don't fink arbitration as a table...try and put customers into one products
into one orders into one order details into one because eventually you'll end up with a
database that has sixty collections for like a hundred major data and you'll be
sighing document...really, really expensive
...you took although lead either...you put into one collection it'll cost you twenty five bucks a month?
So, if we move on let's take a look at the basics of document db okay and
...the understanding of kind of how a resource models put together these...the database
...the poorly credit database account and all that gives use...unique dna serviceable
...like most edges services we fully
...comply we fully race-based...everything in document db is a
raced resource...can talk to at using a raced url everything
from a database to a collection to a user to a permission object to
...itself everything is...object and I can do
...so put so pushes or posts to any resource in the database.
So, that brings...database so databases a psychological thing there isn't
a physical by devices a logical container logical way to group
...collections and...together.
Then we get into collections circulation is really like I said
this container full for different kinds of the documents
it's a physical allocation of resources so when you create a collection we actually go to
a node somewhere in our cluster and we physically allocate you and
At amount of cpu and amount of memory and amount of the sky and amount of network and,
that's how we can might make sure that we don't have a noisy neighbor problem because
that collection has very specific and very hard boundaries
...a cannot operate outside of the boundary some no matter what anyone else is doing in their collection on
their node you're getting that slice of that machine and we make sure that you get
...so that machine.
It's a scope...queries so today you can't do a query across collections
...because a collection could be...any one of our
clusters could be a thousand nodes so you can't do a query that spans across
a thousand nodes what you need to do...talk about the slider is this notion of a fan
out query so if you're looking for...and you don't really know what collection that's in all then you got
...query every collection as a fine art query and consolidate results back together again.
All right our storage...by sdts in...in the machine is solid-state
disks and that's where your data...so we done back on the
edges storage or anything like that there is these.
In fact our index engine has been optimized for modern-day...these
so we...engine that takes advantage of a hardware that we running on.
And, then they're below by the hour so if you create a collection try and you delete
the collection immediately you'll get charge for an hour.
Depending on what that is if it was and sone collection you'll get
charge three-point-four...unknown is three-point-four...
right so just keep that in mind as well when you especially important when you're running
...you running a una taste that's...I...collection does some testing
...collection that's going to charge you that's going to cost you three things to do that.
Right.
And, then you get the notion of documents and a documents is mostly what you're going to work with
that's your document it goes into a collection all right.
Loan for schemer case you can put any kind of documentary like into...one
into one collection and we are optimized for smaller documents rather than
...documents and that's because smaller documents as you may have
noticed if you've done anything on the internet or whatever smaller documents in terms of network io and this guy
I work much better than one large document so decisive
hundred small documents is actually lock lace network io and it's a lot quicker because
I can be paralyzed operations than writing one big
document so we are optimized for lots of smaller documents rather than bigger documents and we
do have a document size limit today which when we started out in preview.
A number that we set that will our internal customers...telling us right
we put out there and very quickly external customers told us that was a very
...number and we...we opted to.
A hundred-twenty ik and eventually we've now up to five hundred twelve
...document now five hundred twelve
...if you take...you...down so get rid of the nice kind of indenting and
wide spice because computers don't need that once you get rid of that five hundred to all kind
of minimize jason is actually an incredible amount of
...right it really is a lot of document lot-of a lot...could fit
into a document plus five hundred twelve k is two little.
And, we're listening we running some internal tests on different document sizes
as soon as we believe that we can from a network io kind of point
of view handling sustain thousand's attendance running bigger documents
we will potentially...that limit again all right so a lot of these limits are implies while.
We're kind of tasting what things can...so,
these are constantly under review and we may well left that limited in the future.
And, then you get other things in document
...called uses...seitenheader user in...and I can assign
...user permissions and use the permissions could be at a collection level or down to a document
...so I could cite this user can only read the document those user can write and read that
...but it's down to a document label we don't have the
...attributes level permission it's down to the document being that we also have
slow procedures...an user-defined functions now before people chase me
...the room with a pitchfork because slow procedures
...server-side triggers and that kind of stuff...we think
they're really all value and benefits...using server-side scripts and for the right
reason like anything no, matter how good it is if you
...incorrectly it's going to be horrible but we believe that if you use a directly
...actually be beneficial for the guys sitting on the floor...the corning unless you want to
...on the floor...sloping
...in the middle over here and there's a few...of their mechanism
right so we also have the notion of attachments what you can do is you can give us
a document that has a picture or video or whatever but
attached to it and we then offload that attachment to blob storage and we manage the
...of that so...delete the document we also go in and clean-up all the attachments with...
well when you query for a document you can get the document back you can also tell us to include the attachments
...bring back the attachments as well all-you-can-eat governance story attachments
yourself propelling to the document...the attachment in the document if you want to do that way.
Okay, so,
document db jason documents this is what I look like they're actually when you look at a
...adjacent documents actually tree.
this is really important because what we base our index on because it's a tree that we can
walken we can navigate through the tree were able to index every property in the document for you.
So, talking about our indexing by default we index every property every
attribute in the document.
We think for the majority of the users.
The default probably good but, we allow you to tweak that we...my changes to
...if you find that you actually ...
Data model really,
really well and you have a big document with a thousand attributes and, you know,
you any...query on a subset of
them they or when there's a lot of fields in a document...being wasted in the
index again that's going to cost you storage size it's going to cost you a
...charges that kinda stuff so you can actually go into index policy and you can do things
like include...paul's so by default we include everything but you can go slot excluding
pods if you want?
We also have two different indexing mods...consistent one is
lazy so default is consistent serve as you writing the document were updating index
...time and we find that the index keeps up and, the very highs
...so we haven't found the index kind of lagging yet
we watch all the time and we've got metrics to tell us whether it's lagging but
...keeps up however if you've got these really big bulk insert kind
of operations so I
...every morning you in just a ton of data.
And, it's not really that important that you can query on...immediately
they what you could do is you could set the indexing policy or indexing mode on a collections lazy
...that'll mean is that we just one index while you're writing and you can
invest a ton of stuff and then the index...catch up in eventually
consistent so you did hire right throughput
worth with lazy mode and then we also have an indexing policy that says automatic
manual right so you can actually switch automatic indexing of completely so when you put a
...collection it doesn't get indexed unless you tell it to be index when you do the create
statement so you can switch automatic indexing off and then only index some documents you
put in the collection some documents you put in the collection you may not
want to index the whole thing other documents...put in the collection you want to index so this way you can switch
on all of depending on what you want to now even if the document has been
...you can still redid as long as, you know, it's id you...
readers all right so you can go in and you can actually read the document by its
...paul's like I said you can kind of include...xthree...
We also have currently two different index types will be adding more as we
go we currently have to indexing types what is a hash and,
that's really, really good for doing equality type operations
give-me all documents where age is twenty or give-me all
...city is san-francisco.
Hash indexes work really well for that kind of operation range index works well for give-me
old documents where ages greater than thirty or where
...between x and y ok so
range operations range index all right now?
Depending on what you're doing you can actually switch, switch index so,
as you include...off you can see over there I'm including.
...including...that...roots...giving it an index type of hash something apply
hash index everything in my document the bottom one I think I'm saying
...time stamp I wanted to be a range because I'm going to do range kind of operations on-chip time
...so that's what you can do over there and then as you start doing these things you can also change the index
precision and index precision is largely a tradeoff between the amount of
storage that we do and a and the speed of the index all of the index
are more precise you are the quicker we will be okay but,
the larger may be less precise ja the smaller you'll storage
requirements will be but the bigger the results...will have to kind of scan through...index.
And, then you do that so javascript transactions all...these things on triggers
in-store proxy allow you to do multiple document transactions so when you want
to do that multiple document transaction slow procedure trigger.
So, what you do...you going you define this whole procedure I'll show you what one looks like or trigger I'll show you
one looks like and that can then go and perform operations
gains multiple documents and either commit the whole thing as a snapshot as
...transaction or effect still procedure
ritalin javascript frozen era we roll back the whole thing and we...everything and put the database
...consistent...
In terms of query there are currently
depending on currently there are two ways to query document db if
...in dot net how many dot net developers and room.
Actually sorry this is a...conference how many non dot net developers in the
audience so node python javascript compliance right cool so.
I'm going to talk quickly about the net stuff and then the other languages we haven't forgotten about so
will be making changes into the other languages soon in dot net you can use
...if you like writing stuff...language integrated query you can I should do that and,
for the most part works there are some up right is that we don't yet support inside of link and that's because the back-end
kind of query capabilities...catching up but,...works and then for the non dot
that people even...the people that still prefer sequel
syntax you can write your query as a sequels sql query.
And, both work equally fine if you're doing race programming you
...sql as the body.
And, you would execute query that way around.
All right what we can also do is we can
...queries by introducing user-defined functions
...one over here is a user-defined function call
...it's written in javascript.
So, you...store on the server and then when
you execute that you can actually then include the you df in your query?
And, you can do some really cool powerful things with you...if
...writing in link this is a shows how to include the you df in sql if you're writing and dot
...you can involve for-you df from link as well so you don't have to...back to sequels you
judea you can use...you df in a way close right so I could
have said select name from company from roots where
...equals company and text greater than.
...I can do that.
Bp warm though that as soon as you put a...into the way close if that's the only
predicate in the way close we then...take advantage of the index right because we
...the xthree ud if so we then would resort back to the
scan and scandal the documents and possum for-you df and that's why I
say have at least one other falter in your query if you're going to use
...and the way close in this case it was like where type is company but I could have said where
hq equals russia and then puts
v you df into that means rule first go to the index final documents
that match from the index and then we'll pause that smaller subset of documents into the
...for rather than every single document that's going to go through the if?
All right so the kinds of applications that we're seeing people both are
your traditional web write the...nodal js
and the back-end we also support other things on the back-end
we have full support for java...if you want to run a java web
...full support for java if you want to run python we have
...support for python that kinda stuff so
...admit node the js on as a websites for instance we also have
php ruby there's some guys...the community of slowed a php
...a ruby driver for us is also now I see a go driver so community
...is picking up really nicely so,...have...get up...and if you want to
...was please do the...js the java sdk the javascript is
to...lol opensource if you want to contribute back to...feel free
dot net one is not...yet there's some?
Internal compliance issues that we're working through to get that one published ...showed we will
...it's just a little bit more work to publish that one but, we'll get...
All right so we can also support so this model here was your traditional kind of
...airwave application you get...web...web server and you
...and how that web server all that web
...the databases using this notion of a mas techy?
That...key used as a storage.
...couple people...gives you a mas...simon's we give them off to
...now with the musty you can do absolutely anything on that database account you can drop...you
can credit collection you can do whatever so you need to keep the key secure and
safe so when you're doing a middle...kind of application like this and that applications running
and measure you can keep key in the middle...a and b very confident that
...your...that...right.
We also want to...of a single page...application the
...one...you have no middle...and the web klein's...strides the
...right now...you don't want to do here is you don't want
to put the key into yours into your web application.
And, also the question but hopefully it's obvious why don't you want to put the key into your web application.
Thank you...that's because the key is
...study on every device that is accessing that thing and you have now given...why your si
...is a password to unanimous is not a good idea so today we
...require that you have a small.
Middle...the client will go...connector and says hey this is...I
...we will then go off to document db we general rights effectively assessed
aiken...access signature for end-user for a period of time.
We then return that...token to the browser and that's what the browser
uses to talk to the database doesn't use the mas techy...uses that short time
...of ...access signature and eventually that's shared
...signature will time-out you can set how long-duration is
...out it has to go back to the middle tier get a new token and then can make back to the database?
So, that's how it works that I.
We don't yet have integration into things like as...active directory so you can't director...
sign in get a token posits document db it's something that were investigating but it's not there
yet we also fully support mobile applications and like you single page apps please
...puts the key in your in your
file nap all-in-all iphone appointee...android...
Again, people get a hold of that app...compile it and
...your key okay so please don't do that either do something similar to what
I had before all use something like...mobile apps.
As...mobile apps
...has the key and the...the...told to the database and all the application
does is authenticate against that and then mobile services or as
...mobile applications proxies local to the database and then using as your mobile
apps you can either writes about that back-end or nodal...back-end and then that's how that works.
I...applications we see lots and lots and lots of kind of I had
to use especially when we hand out things like ruby pies and
...you windows we see lots more people kind of writing these kind of applications
...what we've seen a lot of is when we started out with
a lot of some people would say well okay...try and kind of get my device the
...to the database again a problem because the device needs
...key...don't do that what you want to do is have
devices speak to something that's cheaper and easier and even more
scaleable okay something like as...events...
You get the device to...pleasure events hubs double-a messages in
...there and then you have some kind of a processor to pull out of events
...and stick it...document db...can be something that you custom
bold and run on a worker...it can be something alike I've shown here which is apache
store more measures stream analytics they
...make to events...for you...the data...do real-time analytics on them if you
want to do something with that and then push the results and,
the raw data falls into the as a document the what-you
main do overtime species imc applications that generate terabytes of data
By the end-of-the-year you see...bowl has got to and I watering
really large number so what you want to start doing is you want to...aging out all...so you
...have a process that will go and find data that's old in document db
...talk about strategies to do that in a second...you'll have that process
...out the old data into something like the...data like which was talked about
on by one was...I can't remember but there's now leisure data
...you can dump data into and then you can run your analytics jobs on top
The...like.
So, some things to kind of look at.
When designing and ...the document
db applications so yes there's still some design even though we're...agile kind
of flexible goals cruel there's still some design that we have to kind of do upfront?
We generally say subtle...modeling your data
...right it's easy to kind of remodel united but sort
...some kind of an idea think about how what are these entities that you're going to work with how you going to work
with them how they're going to be query together how's your web application
...mobile application get a query for them use them write them that kind
of stuff so think about your access patterns...
size kind of come up with your top five to ten queries ok now use the real
...that you model this jason and use them in those queries and then what you will
do is every time you execute any operation against document db you get
backer question of charge that
...charges the currency where we all the charge that we applied
to that to that operation so you'll see like if I do a read I get back
...you charge of one if I doa...of a large documentum I get back and...you count of one hundred?
Model...dire your queries.
Measure what...you charges...will help replying...capacity...help you understand with the you need
and sone and stwo and sthree or if you need a thousand is threes or a hundred this
one's or whatever the case maybe that's the only way you will...
But, then measure those are use constantly that will have metrics...the portal
...tell you what you'll average or you count was what was your maximum are you count what was your minimum are
...that kind of some measure that keep track of that and as you see if that
...too high you may want to go back and look at
remodeling your dine or changing your index all optimizing a queries on and those kinds of things.
title modeling with the normalization so the biggest challenge that people coming from a relational
...into a document...is how do I model
medina okay because it's very different from how...model my data in
a relational let's sayI have an application that's dealing with motor vehicles
in a relational database what I would probably do is take at motor vehicle and
...into its thousand individual pots and then I probably
stalls individual parts all over the place and when I wanted to work with...data with
a vehicle...write a query that would join all the tables together and
re bold reassemble my vehicle and a
document advice most of the time what we're doing is saying don't...vehicle down
is stored as it is as an entity ok?
Now these are some things.
...kind of good full so when you're doing one...few relationships ok so here
I've got a person that has a few contact details.
The imbedded data changes infrequently
what I mean by that is if I was linking to I don't know let's say
the address right in this case and the city was washington and it has
...right now if that zip code changes often...
if when you potentially don't want to do that because what you do is you have to
go to every single document that has washington...code.
Whereas in a relational database would be all easier because you've got a one recording chains that in one place
and everybody would know about the change this time think about how many...that
the value that you d normalizing is being...
And, largely d normalizing provides for better read performance
and applications you typically unless you're doing a little bit more complicated
...you typically...compromise either read performance
...performance so you-can either model your data for really, really good read performance...model your data for really,
really good right performance or some kind of compromising between unless you're doing something like secure
rs where you have two different models representing about but typically...normalize
model is better for read why because when I'm reading...I...I did one entity and I
bring it back I don't have to go to fifteen tables reassemble...and bring it back to.
Sometimes the d normalizing is not provide way to go and you can stolen a document
advice do referencing the referencing here is a weakling
...because the server doesn't in full-size links so
...I've said when I inserts and address document with user id xyz
the database won't go insight hey there's no user called xyz therefore you can't do this
...it won't do that
four-year-olds gladly accepted so you could end up with broken links.
You can use a triggering document db to kind of gone enforce that if you want...can create a
...trigger that says when I put in...document my shoulders...
that matches user id if it isn't reject the address document okay so you could do that in a trigger.
Data modeling with referencing is usually better when the reference data
changes frequently so when you want to go in and update that wrote that piece of reference data that's being reference by lots
of other documents think about referencing your data.
The data modeling with referencing when you have a heavy...workload
is often kind of you'll get better performance out of your write workload.
Right you can also aggregate these things so you can have hybrid models
with some of your data is normalize some of you...normalized.
So,...it's...of flick through the slides quite quickly use I want to get to the next part and I'm running out
of time but, some...somewhat jason data modeling...the slides will be available off
...as you can go and have a look at those but some of those things over there make...may seem small but
...very big difference when you model your application?
Indexing policies again I told you can play around with indexing policies and ranges
in precision and all that kind of...queries look which are you charges
modify your index policy do this...agency which are you charges.
Clearing the things that you can do with query to optimize rights...smaller results
...limit the use of scan operations okay so if you don't have a range
...on-the-field don't do a range operation...don't
...queries that say not so often people say
selects...from database where gender is not...
They don't do that.
Because that results in a scanned rather do
a slight star from database where gender equals female if you're looking for
...that's a much more efficient query that will give you the exact same results it
...sighing where a lot of mile so simple things like that if you have
...way clauses include other particles.
All...inductive...db you need to partition for two reasons data
size because every collection is I need to engage in size today
and throughput the maximum collection that you can have is two thousand five hundred
...units per second if you need more than that to serve ten million concurrent
users okay which we have a customer does you need to...across multiple partitions.
How do you scale out so there's a couple of different ways the first is pullover
...start-one petition you...get to some kind of
...room and then you start spilling over to the next one day?
...notion of a range.
So,...for the current period of time
okay today seven days this month this year and then when
that period falls over you move to the next one when appeared
...you move to the next one and eventually you'll in a jobs in pog per jot all
And, then you also have this notion of a lookup so some kind of look up so I'm
...by tenant on petitioning by region and
...by vehicle...number or whatever the case
maybe I have some kind of a short map that I actually look at let me skip this one because
I want to show you what we've just recently announced so if you got to
petition hash says I've got a hundred collections on
...evenly distribute them all data across collections
...you some kind of algorithm and that will then go and spread your data across
...collections for you?
Skip...so, if you take a look...find out queries this is what I was talking about earlier sometimes data
may actually exist in multiple create in multiple containers and you need to do a
...operation now languages like dot
...allow you to do parallel query execution so I can
firewall foes three queries in parallel and one operation and asynchronous
we certain white for the results from each of those to come back to
...aggregate results and present that to my application.
Yes,...multiple...to the device but when you web...sitting in the same datacenters
measure document database its multiple...over sub millisecond
...network infrastructure it's really not that much of a big deal.
All right so when you want to design...the three that I've kind of looked up and they each got some pros and
And, unfortunately there's no one kind of solution that fits
everybody scenario these are largely the three patterns that we seeing
customers doing tonight so I'll look up's ranging and hashing okay.
Partitioning sounds hog and lots of...of come to us and said
...is hard I throughout a lot of extra code please help.
So, just yesterday we announced that we...included petition resolves
...the new...sdk so what you do is your apt talks the
...the apt to figure out what
kind of petition resolve or its using so either hash
...look up a small overall any of those and it...
Talks to the net or poss that...to the done erased entire and
sdk figures out which collection you should...and it goes off to that...collection so
...many collections and we have some customers that have a thousand collections
very now appear as one logical database of anyone's work to
...document db before when you're writing a document you tell us which collections
go put in now you don't you tell us which database to put it in you tell us what
partition resolve you're using and we...out what collections...than all get it from.
There's still able to work that you have to do that so we haven't done a little for-you
...still some work around managing those petitions when you petitions get
to bagel you want to add an extra ones and you want to shuffle data
...work that you have to go do their ...looking at what we can do to make that easier for you
but that's that I will posts all the demos online in fact there
really are so I'll jump to actually where in a second where they are
...there...you...document db partitioning all samples in the demos that
I was going to run are in that folder so I will show you how to go and
use the bolton hash petition resolve
...the bolton range petition...the bolton spa level partition resolving?
And, then we expose...interface called I...resolve...you can go...your...one
day I wrote...for customer ready that was a combination of hash range and,
pullover so they have once I...range...so, I have a range
of things within that I have a hash because I have a number of collections in that range and
then as does collections flap...over to another one so using
...resolve a is basically to methods one that says...for read one that
...create and you go and implement the code that figures out how to do this you can go right
...ones and in that at the url
we've there's about another for different ones that we've actually...we're hoping.
Is that we kind of build-up community of people contributing the
position resolves so if you...a cool...resolving you want to share it please go put it
...a get have repository and, shared with other people and what...we see
more those people we...kind of look to bring it back into the core sdk all that...stuff?
Ok, so, roadmap time I promise
you roadmap I have thirty seconds so let me go through roadmap quickly so we
will public preview in light last year we gi dvs.
Couple weeks ago and,
since then we've done deployments every single week...every single week
...push the deployment we've pushed hundreds of deployments sometimes even more than once a week
and what we've been actually focusing on is making sure that first and foremost the services stable
and...it scales okay so,
yes, there are a couple of features that we're short all right but we needed to make sure that the
bison solid that we can bowl these features on top of so we're
...kind of catching up a little bit and, there's still some foundation
work we're doing and we have a whole bunch of features kind of queued up and the sues
where we feel comfortable those features should role really quickly?
So, showtime future in the next.
I want
...too much in the next weeks we should be able to see name based routing
okay so people have told us that...like self links self links when you
...the...internal your eyes so every resources a has a as a
...it when you create a document we create this internal thing called
the resource id which is unreadable...
You don't know what it is so, you know,
you document bites id you don't necessarily know what...resource ideas in order to go
...read the document what you gotta go do is you gotta go query for it bring it back get sell
...can then use...are applying so what
word bringing out fairly shortly is concept of nine based routing
name base being the id that you've given us...you create a document
called my document id you'll be able to get include that inside url
I have you'll supplied ideas and its instead of just our internal resource
...which will make we hope a huge difference so, we also be doing range
indexes for strings so you can do things like starts with ends with contains.
And, then probably the big one that everybody's writing for is
...auto by is queued it's in our internal
taste environment is going through some serious kind of strange
and tasting and as soon as we feel comfortable vthree features...land and,
all and hopefully very soon I'm hoping to have...that's the and, we're
only just getting going we have features planned for ages okay we're only getting going
...because this is a service it means that
we can deliver features on a weekly vices if we need to on a daily basis if we have
Please keep telling us what the features are please on thing we're ignoring you
...not ignoring you were listening to every single feedback request that comes
in and we feed them into our planning and we feed them into
our prioritizing and every single kind of peace
...feedback...guys give us goes into planning the future of the service so please keep giving
us that and,...was...point because we are looking to grow
...team so there's the feedback in the forms so the
user voice one and the forms if you've got a problem so user voice if you want to feature...
for forms if you have a problem go posted I personally spend way too much time
authoring forms.
And, not responding to other things that I should be doing but that's because I
feel passionately about helping people kind of you...problems that you've
gotten using those problems to learn how we can make the service better in the future
that's a great learning experience for us then the product page in the dachshund tutorials
...looking for more info and more dachshund tutorials weekly publishing you
...need tutorials all the time so please going to have a look...and,
use the feedback if you if you like the document tells you like the document
because that gives us an idea of what kind of documents you like if you don't like the documents tells you are
like intel's why you like it because then we can go and improvement document write.
In samples there's lots and lots and lots and lots and lots of samples we push
up all the time ...I have a look at that one then blogging twitter if you want to follow us on
the blog and on and on twitter that's where we announce kind of cool new things so if you
...following us...yesterday you would have seen announcement of a petitioning
and charting support already so now we're a little bit over so,
do we probably...too much time on the stage doing questions because of run out
of time so sorry about that for the people watching at home but if you have a question please come
find me I will be outside
...so come find me and all happily answer any question that you have?